When you think about the brain,
عندما تفكر في الدماغ،
it's difficult to understand,
تجده صعب الفهم،
because if I were to ask you right now, how does the heart work,
لأنني اذا سألتكم الآن، كيف يعمل القلب،
you would instantly tell me it's a pump.
ستقولون على الفور أنه مضخة.
It pumps blood.
يضخ الدم.
If I were to ask about your lungs,
واذا سألتكم ماذا عن الرئة،
you would say it exchanges oxygen for carbon dioxide.
ستقولون أنها تستبدل الأكسجين مقابل ثاني أكسيد الكربون.
That's easy.
إنه سهل.
If I were to ask you how the brain works, it's hard to understand
اذا سألتكم كيف يعمل الدماغ، إنه شيء صعب الفهم
because you can't just look at a brain and understand what it is.
لأنه لايمكنك فقط النظر إلى الدماغ وفهمه.
It's not a mechanical object, not a pump, not an airbag.
إنه ليس اداة ميكانيكية، ليس مضخة ولا كيس هوائي،
It's just like, if you held it in your hand when it was dead,
إنه فقط، اذا امسكته بين يديك وهو ميت،
it's just a piece of fat.
إنه مجرد قطعة من الدهون.
To understand how the brain works, you have to go inside a living brain.
حتى تفهم كيف يعمل الدماغ، يجب أن تذهب إلى داخل دماغ حي.
Because the brain's not mechanical, the brain is electrical and it's chemical.
لأن الدماغ ليس ميكانيكي، الدماغ كهربائي وكيميائي.
Your brain is made out of 100 billion cells, called neurons.
دماغك مكون من 100 مليار خلية، تسمى الخلايا العصبية.
And these neurons communicate with each other with electricity.
وهذه الخلايا العصبية تتواصل مع بعضها البعض عن طريق الكهرباء.
And we're going to eavesdrop in on a conversation between two cells,
ونحن سنقوم بالتنصت على محادثة بين خليتين،
and we're going to listen to something called a spike.
وسنسمع شيئًا يسمى بجهد السفاة.
But we're not going to record my brain or your brain or your teachers' brains,
ولكننا لن نقوم بتسجيل دماغي أو دماغك أو دماغ معلمك،
we're going to use our good friend the cockroach.
سنقوم باستخدام صديقنا الطيب الصرصور.
Not just because I think they're cool,
ليس فقط لأنني اعتقد أنهم رائعين،
but because they have brains very similar to ours.
ولكن لأن دماغهم يشبه دماغنا بشكل كبير.
So if you learn a little bit about how their brains work,
لهذا إذا تعلمنا قليلا عن كيفية عمل دماغهم،
we're going to learn a lot about how our brains work.
سنتعلم الكثير عن كيفية عمل دماغنا.
I'm going to put them in some ice water here
سأقوم بوضعهم في ماء مثلج هنا
And then --
وبعدها --
Audience: Ew! Greg Gabe: Yeah ...
الجمهور: يع! غريغ غايج: بالفعل ...
Right now they're becoming anesthetized.
في الوقت الحالي إنهم يصبحون تحت التخدير.
Because they're cold blooded, they become the temperature of the water
لأنهم من ذوات الدم البارد، يكتسبون حرارة الماء
and they can't control it so they just basically "chillax," right?
ولا يمكنهم السيطرة على ذلك لهذا إنهم ببساطة "يسترخون،" صحيح؟
They're not going to feel anything,
لن يتمكنوا من الشعور بأي شيء،
which may tell you a little about what we're going to do,
والذي من الممكن أن يخبركم عما سنفعله،
a scientific experiment to understand the brain.
سنقوم بعمل تجربة علمية لفهم الدماغ.
So ...
إذًأ ...
This is the leg of a cockroach.
هذه قدم الصرصور.
And a cockroach has all these beautiful hairs
والصرصور لديه كل هذا الشعرالجميل
and pricklies all over it.
وأشواك في كل مكان.
Underneath each one of those is a cell,
تحت كل واحدة منها يوجد هناك خلية،
and this cell's a neuron that is going to send information
وهذه الخلية هي خلية عصبية والتي ستقوم بإرسال معلومات
about wind or vibration.
عن الريح أو الذبذبات.
If you ever try to catch a cockroach, it's hard because they can feel you coming
إذا سبق وأن حاولت إمساك صرصور، إنه صعب لأنه يستطيع الإحساس بقدومك
before you're even there, they start running.
من قبل أن تقترب حتى، ويبدأ بالجري.
These cells are zipping up this information up to the brain
هذه الخلايا تنقل المعلومات سريعًا إلى الدماغ
using those little axons with electronic messages in there.
باسخدام هذه الألياف العصبية مع رسائل الكترونية بداخلها.
We're going to record by sticking a pin right in there.
سنقوم بالتسجيل عن طريق الصاق دبوس هناك.
We need to take off the leg of a cockroach --
نحتاج لسحب قدم الصرصور --
don't worry, they'll grow back --
لا تقلقوا، ستنمو مجددًأ --
then we're going to put two pins in there.
وبعدها سنقوم بوضع دبوسين هناك.
These are metal pins.
هذه دبابيس معدنية.
One will pick up this electronic message, this electric message is going by.
واحدة ستقوم بالتقاط الرسائل الالكترونية، هذه الرسائل الاكترونية ستمر.
So, we're now going to do the surgery, let's see if you guys can see this.
حسنًا، سنقوم الآن بالعملية الجراحية، لنرى اذا يمكنكم رؤية ذلك.
Yeah, it's gross ...
فعلًأ، إنه مقزز ...
All right. So there we go.
حسنًا. ها نحن ذا.
You guys can see his leg right there.
يمكنكم رؤية قدمه هناك.
Now I'm going to take this leg,
الآن سأقوم بأخذ هذه القدم،
I'm going to put it in this invention that we came up with
وسأضعها في هذا الإختراع الذي جئنا به
called the Spikerbox --
يسمى صندوق جهد السفاة
and this replaces lots of expensive equipment in a research lab,
وهذا يستبدل الكثير من الأدوات المكلفة في المختبرات،
so you guys can do this in your own high schools,
يمكنكم فعل هذا في مدارسكم،
or in your own basements if it's me.
أو في قبوكم الخاص اذا كنت مكانكم.
(Audience: Laughter)
(الجمهور: ضحك)
So, there.
حسنًأ.
Can you guys see that?
هل يمكنكم رؤية ذلك؟
Alright, so I'm going to go ahead and turn this on.
حسنًا، سأقوم الآن بتشغيله.
I'm going to plug it in.
سأوصله بالكهرباء.
(Tuning sound)
(صوت ضبط)
To me, this is the most beautiful sound in the world.
بالنسبة لي، هذا أجمل صوت في العالم.
This is what your brain is doing right now.
هذا مايفعله دماغك في الوقت الحالي.
You have 100 billion cells making these raindrop-type noises.
لديك 100 مليار خلية تصدر هذه الأصوات.
Let's take a look at what it looks like,
لنأخذ نظرة على شكلها،
let's pull it up on the iPad screen.
لنضعها في شاشة الحاسوب اللوحي.
I plugged my iPad into here as well.
أوصلت الحاسوب اللوحي هنا أيضًا.
So remember we said the axon looks like a spike.
لقد قلنا أن الألياف العصبية تشبه جهد السفاة.
So we're going to take a look
إذًا سنقوم بأخذ نظرة
at what one of them looks like in just a brief second.
على واحدة منهم خلال ثواني معدودة.
We're going to tap here,
سنقوم بالضغط هنا،
so we can sort of average this guy.
حتى نستطيع نوعًا ما توسيط هذا الشيء
So there we see it. That's an action potential.
إذًا ها نحن نراها. هذا هو جهد الفعل.
You've got 100 billion cells in your brain doing this right now,
لديكم 100 مليار خلية في دماغك تقوم بهذا الآن،
sending all this information back about what you're seeing, hearing.
إعادة إرسال كل هذه المعلومات عن كل ما تراه وتسمعه.
We also said this is a cell
لقد قلنا أيضًا أن هذه خلية
that's going to be taking up information about vibrations in the wind.
ستقوم بأخذ المعلومات عن الإهتزازات في الرياح.
So what if we do an experiment?
حسنًأ ماذا لو فعلنا تجربة؟
We can actually blow on this and hear if we see a change.
يمكننا النفخ عليه وسماع إذا كان هناك صوت.
Are you guys going to be ready?
هل أنتم مستعدون؟
If I blow on it you tell me if you hear anything.
إذا نفخت على هذا أخبروني إذا أمكنكم سماع أي شيء.
(Blowing)
(نفخ)
(Sound changes)
(الصوت يتغير)
Let me just touch this with a little pen here.
دعوني ألمسه بهذا القلم.
(Noise)
(ضوضاء)
That was the neural firing rate.
هذا كان معدل الحرق العصبي.
That actually took a while in neuroscience to understand this.
هذا فعليًا أخذ وقتًا طويلا لفهمه في علم الأعصاب.
This is called rate coding:
هذا يسمى معدل الترميز
the harder you press on something, the more spikes there are,
كل ماتضغط بقوة أكثر، يزداد أعداد جهد السفاة،
and all that information is coming up to your brain.
وكل المعلومات تصعد إلى الدماغ.
That's how you perceive things.
هكذا كيف تدرك الأشياء.
So that's one way of doing an experiment with electricity.
إذًا هذه طريقة لعمل تجربة بالكهرباء.
The other way is that your brain is not only taking in electrical impulses,
الطريقة الأخرى هي أن دماغك لا يأخذ فقط النبضات الكهربائية.
you're also sending out.
أنت أيضًا ترسلها خارجًأ.
That's how you move your muscles around.
هكذا تحرك عضلاتك.
Let's see what happens if I've plugged in something that's electric
لنرى ماذا سيحدث إذا أوصلت شيئًا كهربائيًأ
into the cockroach leg here.
إلى قدم الصرصور هنا.
I'm going to take two pins, I'm going to plug them onto the cockroach.
سأقوم بأخذ دبوسين، وسأوصلهم بالصرصور.
I'm going to take the other end, I'm going to plug in into my iPod.
وسأقوم بأخذ النهاية الأخرى، وسأوصلها بالحاسوب اللوحي.
It's my iPhone actually.
في الحقيقة إنه جوال.
Do you guys know how your earbuds work in your ears?
هل تعلمون كيف تعمل سماعات الأذن؟
You have a battery in your phone, or iPod, right?
لديك بطارية في جوالك، صحيح؟
It's sending electrical current into these magnets in your earbuds
إنها ترسل تيارات كهربائية إلى المغناطيس في سماعات الأذن
which shake back and forth and allow you to hear things.
التي تهتز ذهابًا وأيابًا وتسمح لك بسماع الصوت.
But that current's the same currency that our brain uses,
هذا التيار هو نفسه التيار الذي يستعمله دماغنا،
so we can send that to our cockroach leg
إذًا يمكننا إرسال هذا إلى قدم الصرصور
and hopefully if this works,
ولنأمل إن عمل هذا،
we can actually see what happens when we play music into the cockroach.
يمكننا فعليًا رؤية مايحدث إذا عزفنا موسيقى للصرصور
Let's take a look.
لنأخذ نظرة.
(Music beat)
(إيقاع موسيقى)
Can we turn it up? There we go.
هل يمكننا تشغيله؟ ها نحن ذا
(Audience reacts and gasps)
(صيحات الجمهور)
GG: So what's happening?
غريغ غايج: إذًا مالذي يحدث؟
Audience: Wow!
الجمهور: مذهل!
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So you see what's moving. It's moving on the bass.
ترون مالذي يتحرك. إنه يتحرك على الإيقاع.
All those audiophiles out there,
كل عشاق الموسيقى هناك،
if you have awesome, kicking car stereos,
إذا كان لديكم ستريو سيارة مذهل،
you know, the bass speakers are the biggest speakers.
هل تعلمون، مكبرات باس الصوتية هي أكبر مكبرات صوتية.
The biggest speakers have the longest waves,
والمكبرات الكبيرة لديها موجات طويلة،
which have the most current,
والتي لديها أقوى تيار،
and the current is what's causing these things to move.
والتيار هو مايجعل هذه الأشياء تتحرك.
So it's not just speakers that are causing electricity.
إذًا ليس فقط المكبرات التي تسبب الكهرباء.
Microphones also cause electricity.
الميكرفون أيضًا يسبب الكهرباء.
(Beat)
(إيقاع)
So I'm going to go ahead and invite another person out on the stage here
سأقوم بدعوة شخص آخر إلى المسرح هنا
to help me out with this.
ليساعدني في هذا الشيء.
So there we go.
ها نحن ذا.
(Beatboxing)
(إيقاع صوتي من الفم)
This is the first time this has ever happened in the history of mankind.
هذه اول مرة يحصل فيها مثل هذا الشيء في تاريخ البشرية.
Human beatbox to a cockroach leg.
إيقاع بشري إلى قدم صرصور،
When you guys go back to your high school, think about neuroscience
عندما تعودون إلى مدارسكم، فكرو في علم الأعصاب
and how you guys can begin the neuro-revolution.
وكيف يمكنكم بدءالثورة العصبية.
Thank you very much. Bye bye.
شكرًا جزيلًا لكم. إلى اللقاء.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)